welcome to the futurists
with ben rhodey and alex lightman today
our special guest
is daniel schmucktenberger who is the
director of research
for the neurohacker collective i love
the name
neurohacker collective the idea is
as far as we'll hear today to bring
together
some of the best uh science and insights
into how to make humans smarter and how
to do a variety
of things so let me uh first introduce
my co-host ben rody say hello ben
hey daniel thank you so much for joining
us
it's a delight to be here thanks for
having me and i want to say too that
this is a special
show because it's our first show that
we're doing while ben
is in a hurricane costa rica
and i'm in santa monica and then um
neither rain nor snow not that he'd have
that much snow but he does live on a
mountain
uh neither rain nor snow nor dark of
night
will keep ben rhody from doing the
futurist show
it must be it must be something i picked
up as a mailman and um
i think that i think it's it's
interesting that we spent the last
30 minutes trying to get the technology
here so i think like
the running joke right now is how many
futurists does it take to get
to be able to record a damn show um yes
and let's say that so we're also we're
pre-recording this show it's
it's uh 7 45 p.m for me
because uh daniel is a vampire has a
vampire schedule
so i'm excited to hear about that at
some point um
and i'm i'm i read in your bio that
about your vampire schedule and says so
as long as you're
able to meet daniel halfway um
we'll get a lot out of it so here we are
meeting uh
meeting the vampire at night and i'm
excited to
buy it into this topic
so first question um we we know about
what's uh daniel what is biohacking and
then within biohacking
what is neurohacking
so biohacking
and neural hacking are both uh kind of
amorphous and emerging terms
biohacking has been you know very
popularized with
bulletproof and dave asprey and tim
ferriss and
people like that helping its emergence
and you know very much
relates to performance enhancements
through
any methodology it relates to kind of
integrative medicine and wellness
but from a slightly different
perspective of
rather than working on the disease model
side of it what can we do
on the fundamental wellness support and
enhancement side of it which
has some crossover with uh prevention on
the disease side
and there's some kind of idea with
regard to hacking that it is
a other than an establishment approach
to uh how to do this so this is not
biohacking is not emerging out of pharma
and
fda sanctioned kind of science it's
emerging out of
citizen science out of uh piecing
together science from different places
for kind of grander hypotheses out of
the fields of
uh elite sports and performance
enhancement and all like that
and neural hacking correspondingly is
you could think of it as a
subset of biohacking or you could think
of it in kind of a venn diagram
the way we think about neural hacking is
really being able to hack the mind brain
interface to be able to optimize
people's cognitive
and psychological well-being
and capabilities so how do we enhance
human experience
and enhance human capacity cognitively
psychologically through
both physiological and psychological
techniques and processes
daniel what would uh what do you think
of the biggest six
testes to date of biohacking or neural
hacking
oh i like this question
well it's a good question uh
i think since these are kind of newer
spaces in the way that they
are emerging some of their success is
that they are
actually emerging spaces where people
are uh finding solutions
to kind of elite performance that didn't
exist in the medical world
that some of the knowledge that had been
in very niche worlds is becoming more
popularly available
and that in kind of the overlap with the
integrative medicine world people are
finding solutions to better health that
they had not found
elsewhere and i would say in better
health and well-being
i would say that there are some good
successes across a number of different
verticals whether we're talking about
athletics and weight and fitness or
sleep optimization or uh you know
cognitive optimization i
i think there's actually a number of
meaningful things that have happened in
all those spaces
well i'd like to tell our audience one
stat in case you're thinking
oh this is kind of cute it's nice it's
just having fun
this folks this is deadly serious you
know when the last time
i bet daniel knows this the last time
that the fda approved a drug for
alzheimer's do you know when that was
i'm gonna say no for everybody okay
it was 2003. it was 13 years ago
so here we have the group of people with
alzheimer's it's one of the fastest
growing
populations in the world and it's
it's exploding and we have not been
we haven't approved a drug now this show
uh takes place
post donald trump being elected
president united states
and i think one of his most interesting
proposals
is that he says there are 4 000 drugs
awaiting approval at the fda
and he wants to accelerate that so what
i see
is that there's a tremendous pent-up
demand
for a better faster cheaper
more effective less less industrial
uh less orthodox way of approaching
health
and achievement of human potential so
daniel what uh
what do you think that we're doing wrong
and what do we need to be doing
better as a society and what role do the
does neuro hack king and the neurohoc
neurohakka collective play in this
that's a lot of big questions um i want
to just kind of speak to
the drug discovery and approval process
and the regulatory processes for a
moment
i think we do need to take a major step
forward in
how we do medicine and how we do
wellness
but it is getting to take an
evolutionary step that is standing on
the shoulders of previous successes
rather than
um things that didn't make any sense
when you think about the history of the
fda we have
the fda really gaining you know a lot of
necessary traction after thalidomide
when a drug that did work for morning
sickness and pregnancy got moved forward
too quickly and
caused meaningful birth defects so
there's this question of if you have
delayed causation
and very meaningful side effects
how much of a longitudinal study do you
need to do
how big of a group needs studied on to
know if there are
rare but very serious effects so these
are not trivial issues
um and so there is a purpose for
appropriate methodology
that we very much respect uh and
i would say the current system has a
number of limitations when we're looking
at for instance animal trials there's a
number of places where
the data we're getting from animal
trials really doesn't cross over into
human biology well enough and it is a
it's both
scientifically and ethically not the
best of how we can do it
moving forward as we start to get into
personalized medicine
and wanting to be able to address an
individual person's health
uniquely differently based on their
genome based on their whole history of
life and exposure their microbiome than
we would someone else
clinical trials aren't an adequate way
to know how to do that because we're not
going to be looking at
one drug intervention we're going to be
looking at
some weighted combination of a number of
different things that might have never
been used in exactly that ratio for
exactly this person before
so getting into n equals one
optimization is a totally different kind
of science
and being able to do more decentralized
science
synthesize what we know across so many
spaces
and include citizen science and i think
these are all parts of
some of the next steps of of scientific
evolution that have to happen
great so if this is the future of
medicine what does this look like
i think the biggest thing that i would
speak to regarding the future of
medicine
because there's going to be evolutions
in diagnostic technologies
evolutions and therapeutic technologies
both on the
surgical acute medicine and on the
chronic uh
you know health side as well as
evolutions in um neural hacking
biohacking for
elite optimization and for radical life
extension there's going to be
technological solutions in all those
areas the thing that i think is most
significant is how it all fits together
which is
a fundamentally upgraded model for
understanding what health and wellness
and biological resilience is and
understanding
what illness is how illness happens in
in a more complex and complete way that
uh doesn't have autoimmune diseases and
neurodigen
and so many cancers um underexplained
but actually can have detailed and
personalized explanations for these
things that lead to
cause level solutions and so if we want
to dive in a little bit deeper
i can talk about what i think and what
we're working on as an emerging
adequate model for understanding health
optimization
and disease prevention reversal i would
love that i just want to make a quick
comment
because some people in our audience will
not have heard the uh the phrase our
term
citizen science so citizen science is
this
emerging area that actually returns us
to some of the golden ages of
of science when people were at home
experimenting in their own laboratories
you know the does
the discovery of oxygen happen in a home
laboratory et cetera
um i chaired a conference on citizen
science the rise of the citizen science
scientist in 2010 at harvard that was
the first
international conference on the topic
and one of my favorite examples
is people discovering stars and galaxies
galaxy zoo you know sort of an open
source way of of
classifying things and also uh folding
at home
going and using people's spare computing
power to do
um basically go and doing protein uh
experiments and analysis that would take
uh
large numbers of people and cost tens of
millions of dollars to do
but volunteers can do it and uh also
a woman went to burger king once who was
a chemist
and they were giving away all these free
colored glasses and she took one at home
crushed it
and then she found that it was toxic and
so with all the scientists and all the
regulatory agencies
one person who didn't who wasn't the
right person in the right place at the
right time
saved millions of people from being
exposed to toxins
uh and i would just give um one more
example of why citizen scientist
uh citizen science is vital right now
there's a big debate about uh trump's
uh appointment of myron ebel i think
to be the new head of the environmental
protection agency transition
and people are saying oh my god it's
gonna we're gonna reduce protections
the fact is that the epa only tracks 13
chemicals and fracking has been used for
000 wells or more and it has 500
chemicals
so i don't see the federal government i
think this is a great metric we can look
at the federal government with all of
its
power and money and 4 trillion a year is
only
tracking 13 chemicals out of 500 but
many of those others ones are toxic so
citizen science is one of the most
important
movements to protect our health and to
come up with new innovations that we can
that we that we have so um i appreciate
you bringing that up
and um now we can go back to the to what
neurohacker collective is doing and i
i can't wait to hear when in the health
and medicine
and human biology space in particular
the rise of quantified self
so all the different kind of tracking
devices
and you know wearables where we can
track heart rate variability or
gsr or so many things and the rise of
uh apps software for tracking cognitive
metrics psychometrics
people's ability to test their own
well-being and even hardware
for people to you know test glucose more
regularly or ketones or anything at home
and there's a huge trend in these kinds
of
decentralized medical technologies and
wellness technologies emerging
this doesn't give us traditional
placebo-controlled clinical randomized
research but it does give us
meaningful data over very huge data sets
that we can do statistical analysis on
as that data starts to be shared in
meaningful and structured ways
so i think one of the reasons that we
have this rise of
citizen science is that we have
so much more access to actually
scientific tools decentralized
scientific tools
and then access to information
processing that we didn't have
previously in the form of like you're
mentioning
advanced computational capabilities to
do protein folding
and you know one of the things for
instance that our company is working on
right now
is an app that can synthesize
biometrics and psychometrics from many
different sources into
one platform and then not only look at
those biometrics
with regard to you know where the
numbers at on a reference range but
where all the numbers are at in
relationship to each other
factoring all the complex causation
that's known about
wow i'm just i'm listening to so when i
listen to your talk i i notice the way
that
your brain works that that like i'm
imagining
being inside of your brain and
and the way that you speak is so like
yes
it's so technical and it's so academic
and i remember
i'm thinking about reading your your bio
and uh one of your bios that i really
liked was
um you said i didn't have to unlearn all
the stuff that
basically everybody's taught through the
current education system and that you
were raised on buckminster fuller
and and uh just all these amazing great
minds
and so i'm i'm just i'm i'm i'm
i'm appreciating that in you and and and
so
um i don't want to change the subject if
alex has another question about
about this and i do want to get into
this because i ordered some of your
i got on the monthly plan because um
my friend daniel raphael highly
recommended it and he said it changed
his life forever
and so so i'm looking forward to
getting my my first shipment so i have i
have i have more questions about that
but
um i would like to hear about your
just the way that you see the world like
like how do you see the future and how
do you create the future
that maybe most people
most people's brains don't work like
this
we could have a conversation sometime on
the future of education i
i did have this unique fortunate
uh childhood where my parents were
educational theorists and they wanted to
run an educational experiment and this
was before
the term unschooling uh which has kind
of evolved since then
which was raising us without any
curriculum at all but exposing us to
everything
that they could expose us to in terms of
different topics
this is what we're doing with our kids
awesome
and then yeah they were just seeing
where there were areas of interest and
seeing how to facilitate them so
i didn't you know i didn't learn whole
areas of
uh spelling grammar american history
that one would
normally learn have illegible
handwriting but i did get to dive
much more deeply into the sciences and
into activism and into
many world philosophies uh then
one would otherwise have the opportunity
to do and because i didn't have
subject divisions i didn't think of the
world in compartmentalized ways there
was a
conversation would move between
neuroscience
and then looking at what's actually
happening at an atomic level
understanding
so astrophysics to complexity science
for how to put it together for deeper
underlying you know philosophy around
reductionism and
mind brain interaction that was just one
conversation called how do we go about
adequately understanding the nature of
reality
so when what that means in terms of uh
overarching perspective is whether we're
talking about social issues or
environmental issues or
human biology issues one of the
core things that i think that we are not
doing adequately currently
is understanding all of the various
areas of uh interconnectedness and
layers of cause and effect
so when we're dealing with climate
change and we're talking about
carbon taxes or whatever kind of
approaches for climate change that
don't get to fundamentally what all
really has to happen
to address not emitting greenhouse gases
and sequestering them adequately and so
you look at why is sequestration
decreased of what are all the ways that
we cause
deforestation damage to uh you know any
kind of
photosynthesis on land on in water dead
zones and oceans
you think about all the different kinds
of agricultural fluents industrial
fluids that are involved
the economic drivers of it the
underlying economic drivers underneath
the you know energy economy an adequate
solution
involves a lot of things and so we
mostly do kind of a symptomatic approach
that doesn't deal with the whole
causal taxonomy and that's the same in
medicine
and so this is actually very interesting
when we talk about why
the systems have to evolve is when we
have a for-profit medical system
where ultimately patients are customers
and the you know maximizing the lifetime
value of patients
means maximizing lifetime value of
customers which is something that
when you're doing the numbers of running
a business is an automatic
kind of calculation if we can figure out
how to address symptoms there's
obviously
more duration in that profit stream than
preventing things
from happening at all or quick cures are
so it's like
where did the r d budgets even go
there's where there is
fiscal incentive for the wrong things
where you have
some of the most powerful organizations
in the world have their own
ongoing existence and the
health well-being of everyone not
aligned
and you know from an economic
perspective it's not their fault as
organizations it's a structural issue
where you can say theory of markets
really shouldn't apply
yeah well they have shareholders to to
please and all this so
so now you're you're you're mentioning
ways that people at home
will be able to
monitor their own blood sugar and their
their own health
and and like devices that will uh
tell you what's in your food so what's
the you know i've seen a lot of
different devices
that do a lot of different things but
what's the most comprehensive
device that if i had one device that
would do everything
is this has this been invented is it
being invented i think i saw a
kickstarter campaign
of a device that looked like it was
going to do this like read your palm
like took a reading from some skin on
your palm or something and
like this is one of the really big x
prizes right now is for the tricorder
devices
and the tricorder uh medical devices are
both
for being able to do you know medical
diagnostics in rural places where you
don't otherwise have access to
formal medical diagnostics but it's also
for at home
diagnosis and assessment the
the one that i think is probably most
promising so far is the gene
radar technology it's at least one of
the best ones that
anita goal and group from nanobiosim
have developed which has
the ability to look at pathogens
specifically with better accuracy
than pcr analysis but without needing to
draw blood just on the drop of blood
and that and then they'll be able to
move beyond pathogens most likely the
key is moving from needing chemical
reagents to study the blood to actually
being able to study the blood on a chip
so you can study many more things
accurately with much less
blood and much less turnaround time and
processing involved
i think there are metabolomic solutions
for sweat for urine etc that can move
from
chemical reagents to uh processing on
ships that are emerging that are going
to be really transformational
and one of the areas that i personally
have a lot of belief in that's in the
very early stages is laser
interferometry
for being able to actually just bind
beams of light into
the you know through the skin into the
blood and then based on the chemistry of
the blood you get different diffraction
patterns you can read the diffraction
patterns and as we learn the diffraction
patterns of more molecules
we could theoretically get the ability
to assess almost everything that's
happening in the blood in real time
and you can start to imagine what it
means to have continuous
data on an individual person processing
in real time on the cloud
where we can really separate and across
a huge number of biometrics where we can
really separate
correlation and causation because we can
see which things change first
and so we can get big data on a single
person and then also across many people
and start to get very early predictive
analysis for things
and start moving towards really
customized personalized medicine
wow it may sound like it's like it's
instrumental overkill
but daniel makes a very good point um i
asked this question i have a bunch of
questions that i like to ask people that
nobody ever gets right and one of them i
i ask is how many chemical reactions
are happening in your body you know you
can pick whatever period of time but if
i say per second
nobody ever gets it like some people say
10 some people say 100
but the real answer is
there are basically there are a trillion
a tr a trillion chemical a trillion
chemical reactions
per second yeah it's
we you know we don't know how to
estimate this appropriately and every
time we think we do
we have another discovery not that long
after where it goes up by some orders of
magnitude but
a trillion metabolic functions per
second per cell
is a current reasonable estimate and
then when you start thinking about you
know time synchrony across those and
then when you start thinking about
sub chemical right information
processing uh
that might be happening it's it's a lot
of information and that's
one of the things that really we have to
understand about human physiology is
that it's a
self-organizing complex system and
complex systems and complicated systems
are very different
complicated systems like a circuit board
are not self-organizing they are
designed from the outside
they're not fundamentally adaptive and
they don't have causal closure all
over all of the input output feedback
loops so self-organizing systems
are a very unique thing and
understanding them actually requires a
different kind of scientific approach
where you can't remove the variables
understand them in isolation put them
back together and think you understand
it well because the variables
because of combinatorics they actually
do different things in relationships
than they do separately
and the synergy ends up being like like
the cell
respirates even though no molecules that
make up the cell respirator on their own
it's a synergistic emergent property
of that order of complexity and so a
reductionist approach will give you
partial but
fundamentally inadequate information so
when we look at
neurodegeneration or any of the kind of
complex diseases part of it is that we
can't
split the body up into uh neurology and
oncology and gastroenterology
and because gastroenterology we can see
gut brain access stuff micro
biome disorders that are causing
neurologic issues the system is too
interconnected
to be separated that way there are
bottom-up processes controlled by
genetics and top-down processes can
controlled by neuroendocrine process and
connectomics
that interact with each other to create
these very dynamic non-linear
equilibriums
we have to kind of understand how all
those things work and how all the
different variables operate
differently in relationship and so this
is why complexity science
is really necessary for understanding
biosystems well
and then when you start thinking about
not just biosystems but biopsycho
environmental systems
where your body is affecting your
psychology but your psychology
is affecting your body in turn through
kind of psychoneuroimmunological
interactions and your environment is
affecting you and vice versa
to really understand those needs at a
different framework
for understanding complex causation and
that's actually what i think is at the
core
of the future of medicine is and it's
where we take
incurable diseases where we don't
actually understand the cause and it's
because the cause is not the same thing
every time the cause can be very
different things
for this so two different people's ms
doesn't necessarily have the same cause
we can find
statistical correlations of specific
pathogens like
borrelia burg de ferrai which has some
correlation in light of matman's work or
certain funguses that have correlation
or
certain neurotoxins either heavy metals
or organophosphates
or certain genetics or certain kind of
nutritional deficiencies but the reason
that none of them are one-for-one
correlations is because there's a number
of different deviations
from homeostasis that can lead to the
kinds of pathophysiology and causal
cascades
that lead to those tissues and systems
having those kinds of disorders
and so we need a an adequate map
of how multifactorial
complex causal cascades work to then be
able to do
differential diagnosis across them to
find out exactly
what weighted combination of which
factors are involved for which people
and then being able to customize both
medicine and optimization for them
okay so pay me a picture what does this
look like
like let's say there's somebody at their
house they want to figure out
what's my health look like and or what
caused my ms
um and what can i do about it
and so like what what does this machine
do this
this gene uh this gene machine like
what does it do how do they use it and
how does it like
paint a picture for us that just
creates like that would create the value
proposition that would make us say oh i
get it that makes sense
okay so um what i'm talking about right
now
is actually diagnostics complex system
diagnostics and interpretation based on
modeling
and based on understanding
more complexly causation and
where the causation is not obvious so
causation
with a gunshot is obvious right there
are certain things where we have very
clear causation then we know how to
how to treat it but when we're dealing
with very delayed causation where some
some cause happens and the effect
doesn't happen in the obvious way for a
long time
that's actually tricky or when there are
multiple causes
that actually all kind of have a
confluence together into an emergent
set of phenomena that's tricky or when
something has a cause in one system and
then it's affecting a different system
or different set of tissues
those require a different understanding
of how cause and effect
works and so um
i would say like this think about in
order to
give you the value prop i actually need
to explain the model a little bit and
then it'll make sense
so think about what
our bodies are as these complex adaptive
systems these regulatory systems they're
basically regulating
your temperature and your ph and the
levels of so many different
uh you know biomarkers and processes so
it's a it's a homeostatic
regulatory dynamic regulatory system
where all the different regulatory axes
are interacting with each other to
make this adaptive system and then
we can define illness
and decreased health
in terms of we can think about
aging and decreased health as decreased
resilience of the homeostatic
system decrease regulatory capacity
because either there is
less range that can be regulated over or
less
uh ability to move disequilibrius
movements
out of homeostasis back into homeostasis
quicker and so one of the things we want
to do is to support the underlying
homeostatic not the homeostasis of the
system the levels of where things are
what your cholesterol levels are
this is less interesting than supporting
the homeostatic
capacity of the system to self-regulate
so many things in dynamic equilibrium
with each other in relationship
to what's actually happening in the
environment so we want to
and this is you know this is how do we
support things like
cellular energy and you know the atp
production process how do we support
things like autophagy and
all of the all of the aspects of just
how homeostasis happens
systemically and this is kind of we can
think about as
prevention of illness and supporting
life extension
and then we can also think about illness
as wherever there's some deviations from
homeostasis
that exceed the homeostatic capacity of
the system to stay within physiologic
ranges
and then the result is pathophysiology
changed physiologic function uh that
starts
to create pathology and so when we think
about it that way
we'd say okay so before someone gets a
particular autoimmune disease we can see
that certain inflammatory markers
elevate so we can say inflammation
caused it but something caused the
inflammation
something caused the hormone imbalance
whatever those are intermediary markers
so they're part of a causal cascade but
they're never going to be the tier one
deviation from homeostasis because
they're messenger molecules
and so you have to say you know what was
their initial stimulus and the initial
tier one deviation from homeostasis for
any complex system
is always going to be some overarching
behavior of the system
or some interface of the system with its
environment that's not aligned with what
its regulatory system can process
and so if we say
in interaction with the environment we
mean if it if the system if the body
takes in too much of something
that it can't process we call that
toxicity
or pathogenicity or if it takes in not
enough
of something we call it deficiency these
are tier one
deviations or if the if the system
doesn't exercise enough or doesn't sleep
enough or
uh you know bad posture those are
overarching behaviors
of the system that are not aligned with
again what its homeostatic systems
evolve to be able to process and work
with
so we can actually formally identify all
of the
tier one causes and then we can
sub taxonomize everything that happens
all the toxins all the pathogens all the
nutrient deficiencies all the genetic
disorders etc
and then we can look at all the causal
cascades
and then this gives us the ability to
say these are the things
we're looking to do diagnostics we want
to look at both what's happening at a
causal cascade level
inflammatory markers hormones etc and
at an initial cause level pat
uh you know pathogenicity toxicity
deficiency etc
can you still hear me yeah you're doing
great
and then um
so this starts to give us a basis for
both wellness optimization prevention
and then when someone has a specific
illness being able to identify
specifically what's going on
and how to reverse those deviations from
homeostasis while
non-specifically generally increasing
system result
resilience and robustness so what would
that mean from a
you know visualize a practical point of
view it means
if you actually think about how many
different kinds of medical assessment
we have and just even if i'm even just
talking about blood markers
and not looking at electrophysiology or
anything else
between all of the rheumatologic
assessment and toxicologic
assessment and metabolomics and and
you know all the comics right
transcriptomics genetics etc there
right now it's a tremendous amount of
blood from different labs that has to be
drawn with a lot of cost
and you know accuracy issues on many of
them
if you start thinking about what it
would mean to be able to get
all of that data and oftentimes you
think well that data is not relevant for
the kind of condition i have that's one
of the things that we find that is not
the case is that the system is so much
more
interconnected that in sometimes why
we're saying it's an idiopathic illness
meaning we don't understand
you know why it's happening is because
we're not looking at the right types of
causes non-obvious
causes so we want to be able to look at
all of the different things that could
be part of a causal cascade that lead to
leads to what's going on and then be
able to do data analysis across the
whole thing
so imagine in the future that
we start getting the ability to do
diagnostics
much less expensively much more easily
across
many more biometrics more accurately and
then be able to interpret what those
mean across this kind of complex
causation model
and then the machine you're talking
about is actually an ai system
not like a sentient ai but a
combinatorial ai
that can um process
you know a tremendous amount of data
against a
and a causal ontology that's ever
evolving
and actually you know be able to help
doctors physicians you know whomever
identify
specifically what's going on in terms of
the pathological cascades
and in terms of the kinds of things that
could be the upline causes of those
pathological cascades
and then be able to reference for every
pathway that's involved
what the best current therapeutic
technologies are and then
what the right order of operations and
the right synergy of those technologies
are to actually be able to address
what's going on for someone
well that sounds like the most
complicated thing i've ever heard in my
life
dr house at scale
so i'm glad you're working on this
instead of me
so a really good diagnostician does is
they do this they factor
thinking through causation more
complexly it's just it's beyond what any
individual human can do and we want it
to be widely available
and so that can be done through
technology yeah that's great
um do you consider yourself a human
or do you consider yourself technology
i think that's a false dichotomy
you can be both okay so
so talking about causation one of the
things that
that i've explored is
the is illness happening in the body as
a sign
right what's the you know like we've all
the stories of somebody gets cancer
and they've um
you know and then they quit their job
and go live their life purpose and
and then forget about the cancer cancer
goes into remission and
you know it's kind of like it was a
wake-up call right so and i know that a
part of your
genius cross-contextualizing your genius
uh is is you've got the scientific
background and then you've also got the
shamanic background
and the philosophy and so so what are
your thoughts
on you know the difference between
biomarkers and
and chemicals and and the environment
creating
an illness and the the the um
you know the mind the the psycho
somatic reasons that the the the
the markers in our dreams that are here
to wake us up or remind us to pay
attention to
to our body what what are your thoughts
on all that
let's talk about the environment and the
psyche because they're both very
interesting things that are not well
enough addressed
how we think of medicine usually so on
the environment side
if we have agricultural processes
where the deplete topsoil and deplete
trace minerals and topsoil so no matter
uh what people are eating and if they're
eating well
they are getting decreased trace mineral
uh density from an evolutionary
environment
factoring affecting the trace minerals
in the soil factoring the microbiome in
the soil factoring the
uh hybridized seeds you know so many
things
do you think real quick just uh on
on this topic are do gmos contribute
to uh loss of
the nutrients and what do you what do
you think about that just as a quick
aside
i wouldn't address it as a whole
category i would say we could get into
each one but
yes that is a real potential and
not but it's not just gmos even
hybridizing
crops uh effects you know as we're
breeding for more sugar or more
you know fruiting we're also breeding
for less of some things it might have
been very
relevant parts of you know our
evolutionary relationship with those
plants
but as you look at having something like
mineral and microbiome deficiency
ubiquitously in mass
or then you look at environmental
toxicity
everything from the environment of
inside my house where my
my paint and my flooring all have high
voc output volatile organic compound
output where most of those vocs are
either
carcinogens or neurotoxins or endocrine
disruptors
and then you know you go outside and
whether we're talking about from coal
plants or from
cars or from so many sources the
you know ubiquitous kinds of
environmental toxicity where we can
run mother's breast milk run toxicology
on the united states and find hundreds
of distinct petrochemicals and mother's
breast milk and you think about what's
happening to the babies that are
evolving in that
right and that's not just people who
live in in the center of industrial
zones that's
everybody and so when you think about
a world where the way we've done
infrastructure has
deficiency and toxicity and because of
things like mrsa
and pesticide resistant and fungicide
resistant bugs
weird mutated pathogens
in mass can you this becomes a deep
question
can you have optimized people in
a highly damaged biosphere wow
no right so the future of medicine has
to be the future of everything too
oh that's good
and so you know we'll we haven't even
spoke to the psychology side yet which
is individual but it's also systemic if
you have a macro
economy where people are fundamentally
stressed out about money and surviving
and you're asking what's the effect of
psychology and stress on
health it's significant right yeah
there's so many kinds of degenerative
disease
so as part of the future of health care
a better macroeconomic system
has to be if you have a macroeconomic
system
you know political systems that cause
war war is not good for health
and neither is in
neither is industrial process that
causes environmental externality because
there is no externality on a tiny
biosphere floating through outer space
where everything is interconnected with
everything else and so ultimately the
future of medicine what we're talking
about the future of human
wellness is that we are fundamentally
interconnected with everything else
happening on the biosphere and
any place where we are externalizing
harm it's not really external
we just aren't calculating the cause and
effect of it
so we can talk about the future of
medicine from the point of view of
working just on individuals
even if they're within an environment
that is actually a cause of pathology
itself but we have to then go beyond
that and say how do we have the
environment
the mac you know individual homes and
then also macro environments
be a cause for regeneration rather than
for ill health
and it it really does involve nothing
less than
fundamental redesign of civilization
from scratch
from a infrastructure level and a
political
socioeconomic level and that's exactly
what we're doing at rise
that's it yeah that's good
that's good okay so i know we don't i
know we're gonna say
oh yeah yeah yeah go ahead do people's
brains and bodies of and imbalances and
hormones neurochemistry etc
affect their psyches absolutely do
imbalances in people's psyches from the
way they allocate meaning and what they
focus on and their definition of success
and
identity uh does that affect their
physiology
absolutely uh can we reduce
mind to brain it's very problematic to
try
and but it's the it's kind of a given
within the way we think about science
because science system
is a philosophic system it's a method of
knowing right it's an epistemology
but it's based on measuring stuff so it
can only understand measurable
third-person stuff
and consciousness is not independently
measurable third-person stuff it's
first-person stuff
yeah and so it's fundamentally outside
the domain of science
so all science can do is measure the
neural correlates of consciousness what
is someone's eeg doing
when they describe they're experiencing
something but
that might be a neural correlate and
there's a lot
that we need to say about how to even
infer properly
but that that's not first person
experience right and
so we can have a deeper philosophic
conversation around
ultimately what is the nature of the
real does
this physicality emerge from
consciousness does consciousness emerge
from
complex neural networks do they co arise
in some kind of structured pan psychism
but what we what we can say without
getting into all that right now
is that people can
do different things psychologically
that affect their health and the placebo
study is a classic example
right placebo is thinking they're going
to get well
and feeling correspondingly less worried
and more hopeful
and then getting some degree of
improvement symptomologically or
pathophysiologically and then you're
like but if the body's trying to
optimize health all the time why
wouldn't it have done that anyways and
it's because
the chemicals that mediate feeling
that's actually question
but it's because if you feel shitty
anxious angry whatever
that that emotion is neurochemically and
you know hormonally mediated and what
just happens to be very interesting is
that most of those emotions
are sympathetically mediated which
actually does not support
the regenerative processes of the body
and when someone relaxes feels more
hopeful and then feels
better that can support parasympathetic
nervous system engagement and
physiologic regeneration and there's
there's a lot of actual physiologic
pathways that are involved in people's
emotional and cognitive experience and
so
um this is why i would say psychology by
itself is not adequate because someone
can have physiologic disorders
they're not going to psychotherapy away
or meditate away
and medicine by itself is not adequate
because the complexity of
the information processing that's
happening inside of someone's
consciousness
is not reducible to gross neurochemicals
great answer great answer
do we lose alex alex
hey there buddy we lost him um
anyway you and i are still here and i'm
in a costa rica hurricane
he's on a landline in santa monica so
my question to you so i i know we've got
to go here in a few minutes
um i want to hear i want to hear two
things i want to hear
quickly about your your sleep habits
um i i thought about and i tried a long
time ago to do polyphasic
sleep it sounds like that's not quite
what you're doing you just have a
is it just a backward sleep uh
cycle yeah
this is nothing particularly interesting
uh there are
kind of sleep hacking techniques like
polyphasic that some people do that i
have done
in the past but i have uh since the
earliest i can remember in childhood
been nocturnally oriented and
while i have forced that
schedule into a diurnal schedule for
world purposes a number of times
it always is more natural for me to be
on a nocturnal schedule
and my my actual clarity of thinking and
productivity and all like that is best
during the quietest hours um and so
i it seems that there some of it just
might be preference but it also seems
that there might be uh
some groups of people who for whatever
reasons have different circadian rhythms
wow that's so cool i mean i i've thought
about this
and especially when i was looking at a
polyphasic sleep
like there's nobody texting you calling
you messaging you
like my phone's blowing up the whole the
whole day when i'm uh
the whole during the day right and so at
night you just get to focus and and
work your magic without the distractions
this is why i love it
i i've actually been here the whole time
i we are using
a new system and i couldn't find the
unmute button
uh so i finally found it daniel i had a
question for you
how can how can i get smarter
um what's smarter is a word i would want
to dive into a little bit
whether you mean increased short-term
memory or long-term memory or speed of
memory or focus or attention or more
knowledge or
all every way that i can get smarter by
every measure i want to do that
yeah um so
this is this is the neurohacking space
right and
so there are uh chemical approaches uh
the whole field of notropics and brain
nutrients and smart drugs
are all about exactly this how to be
able to
hack biochemistry and neural chemistry
for
affecting cognition either as a whole or
very specific cognitive processes
there's also you know tdcs tms different
forms of
you know transcranial stimulation that
people will use
transcranial lasers try and hyperclock
atp in particular regions their brain
um there are uh microbiome solutions to
kind of increase
the normal healthy neurotransmitter
output that might be decreased in their
gut so there's a lot of like
i would say biochemical solutions there
are
future solutions that are not available
yet but in process
that are things like you know crispr
genomic solutions that actually
change genetic predispositions towards
brain function
um there's obviously brain computer
interface uh
technologies in process um and
this is all kinds of things on the
physiologic side
and then on the information processing
kind of
on the software side um
there's a lot one can do there so i
would say
um the more one
learns about any domain and consciously
thinks about
the cross-applicability of that like why
is this domain the way that it is
thinking through everything else you
know it does this commentary with the
rest of my knowledge making an
interconnected database where you don't
have arbitrary subject
delineations to apply what you know from
thermodynamics to
biologic systems and gain interesting
insights right from
from different kinds of systems and then
the larger just
net database of knowledge you have and
the more interconnect
that knowledge set is the more kind of
insights you will have for lateral
application
to any new topic that comes when you
think about even if i don't know this
topic well
i know a lot about universe surrounding
that topic that can have
cross applicability and then also
frameworks for thinking
so studying systems thinking and
uh things like integral methodology
and uh complexity and
critical thinking where one actually has
better abilities to vet
if things are true or not quickly to
know
all the perspectives necessary to assess
a particular situation well and then how
to synthesize those perspectives
the you know actually studying
epistemology studying the
processes of thinking and knowing is
very useful
wow cool so now with your
thank you very much now i didn't say
there the basics
are make sure you sleep enough because
you'll lose cognitive ability very
quickly if you're not sleepy enough make
sure that you eat well make sure that
you exercise
make sure that your water blood sugar is
stable
all of the basics of a healthy
physiology so that you actually have
healthy brain and information processing
um make sure that you you know
meditation
and the right kinds of psychotherapy in
life that you can actually
focus well uh and you have a brain that
is not
over anxious or over stressed out you
know these these are all
different things so you know what we're
actually working to do at neurohacker
collective is
kind of vet all of the different types
of neurotechnology
that can help cognitive optimization
and on the physiologic side and
on the learning and uh
you know psychological side vet all of
the processes
techniques technologies and say which
ones
move what kinds of metrics for what
kinds of people involving what kinds of
pathways
and then once betting those how do we
synthesize
all of those partial answers to be able
to then make available
the best of human knowledge with
progressively more personalization and
customization
to each person so you know to just make
it kind of
simple say someone was asking
asking about how to become smarter is a
very broad thing we could kind of dive
into
uh specific subsets but for
for illustration purposes say someone
wants to address
anxiety well how much of their anxiety
is physiogenic and how much is
psychogenic
and then of the psychogenic stuff if
someone was not anxious as a kid and
then they had kind of acute
adult trauma that led to ptsd or someone
that was always
anxious from kind of early childhood
attachment theoretic structures
even though those are both psychogenics
they they actually
don't lend themselves equally well to
the same kinds of psychotherapy
and on the physiogenic side anxiety from
a gut brain access disorder
that needs microbiome processing or from
mild head injury
or from a genetic methylation disorder
or from
excitotoxicity from neurotoxins like
again
those are all real uh
causes of pathology and they need
addressed differently so we can just say
like i've got a hammer so everybody is a
nail
everyone should do breathing techniques
so they should all do vipassana
or they should all take a benzodiazepine
and we'll get some effect
everybody on a bell curve if we want to
put everybody on the front end of a
customized bell curve
we have to be able to assess what are
all the things that could be
involved and what they're looking for
how do we assess what's actually going
on for them
and see where the greatest lift is going
to occur
okay so now so your product uh
qualia is that how you say it yeah
i'm so excited to uh get my first
shipment
um how does this how does this
actually affect the brain and
what like what what are some things that
people notice when they first start
taking it like what is what are some
things i have to look forward to
um so quality is the first product that
the
neurohybrid collective as an
organization has
made available recently brought to the
market we have uh
many other products in the kind of
biochemical nutraceutical space
that are in development not currently on
on the market including uh more
personalized versions of qualia
um and then also things in other areas
of neurotech
but uh this was something that was able
to
address a specific need we were
interested in which is when you see that
there are
something like 15 billion dollars a year
in uh
energy drink sales and something like
estimated five billion dollars last year
in
off-label adderall sales for people
using it as a smart drug
so many other smart drugs like that and
this kind of exponential rise
of desire for increased
productivity in a world where people
feel both more
demand and more things competing for
their attention and damaging their focus
and you either have kind of some
vitamin herbal solutions that don't
really do
anything obvious for people or you have
things
like some of these you know either
excessive amounts of stimulant or
off-label pharmaceuticals that can do
something
but oftentimes it's a very partial
result with pretty meaningful side
effects
we wanted to see can we actually
increase
elements of cognitive capacity
neurochemically in
a way that had a much more broad set of
cognitive benefits where we were not
just increasing
focus through a dopamine energy process
but we were addressing
attention span and concentration and
speed of memory and verbal fluency and
digit span and you know all of the
different sub aspects of cognitive
capability along with the
emotional traits that need to come along
like uh emotional resilience
and uh you know the kind of drive
necessary to follow through and not
procrastinate so we were looking at
kind of cognitively modeling when people
want to take when people are seeking
cognitive enhancement what are they
really seeking and they're seeking
the ability to go into creative
productive flow states where their full
cognitive capacity is available
uh more readily being able to go into
those states so we modeled
what are those states from a cognitive
point of view
and then we looked at what are all of
the physiologic systems that mediate
each of those functions that we know of
and what can we do
to support and enhance
the function of those underlying systems
and so qualia
was you know a number of years of
refinement and development
specifically intended to do that to
support the underlying
systems that mediate those kind of
creative
productive flow states and to do so in a
way that
is not only causing some immediate
effect but it's also in
it's supporting the body's own
regulatory processes rather than
overwriting them
so that rather than leading to
dependency it's leading to
increased system resilience even after
someone stops using it
great cool it must feel really good to
having been worked
working on this for so long to have it
complete
and and people benefiting from it
already i've heard a lot about it
what are some of the other things that
you're working on that that we can look
forward to
uh if you can talk about it the next
handful of things
that are likely able to come out are
going to be
um more personalized
versions of qualia where people are you
know seeking a similar goal right
they're seeking
increased cognitive clarity and
availability to create great work
you know while having good states of
human experience
but being able to address more different
kinds of physiology types so we're
working on
customization which doing that at scale
is tricky but we're uh we're getting
close
and we're also working on support for
uh other goals like sleep and calmness
and fun
weirder things like meditation and lucid
dreaming support
oh yeah cool let's do that then
i'll take i'll take one of those too
thank you
yeah i mean there there we have to
separate what is interesting
scientifically
and what is doable from a regulatory
process so
you know there's a tremendous body of
data supporting psychedelic assisted
psychotherapy is actually being
uniquely capable of addressing certain
kinds of issues more quickly than
anything else
and it's very silly that we still have
the regulatory process around it we do
it is not
good law um but obviously we have to
work in
what we can do both from a scientific
and a regulatory point of view
daniel i wish we could talk longer uh
this is almost
all the time we have i have one more
question for you
yeah we we end each show
in a similar way we ask our guests
to give our listeners three things that
they can do
uh related to the show so in your case
what are three ways
that people can improve their
intelligence
their health or their ability to engage
in
citizen science perhaps perhaps one of
each
um okay so a good way to improve your
health and intelligence that
this is not going to be novel but
hopefully
if we've developed any rapport over the
conversation i can add to
what one knows about it is uh
sleep well and enough
it's the more we study sleep the more
profound its effects on cognition and
physiology are
memory consolidation is almost
exclusively happening during slow wave
sleep delta sleep and if someone's not
getting enough
slow wave sleep not only are there
physiologic effects and uh
the body does so much of its antioxidant
and anti-inflammation and et cetera
worked in
but memory consolidation is is very
limited
um and that's how much is enough sleep
how do we know
this is genetically different for
different people and then even for the
same people if they have things going on
with their physiology or how much
they're working out or what their stress
loads are it'll all be different
uh for most people uh this is in the
eight hours of uninterrupted uh sleep
that's ideal some people need less than
that and if someone has something going
on with their physiology or they're
under a lot of strain working out very
hard they might need more than that age
is a factor
um but a way that you can know is that
you wake up feeling refreshed and have
good energy throughout the day
and if you have to wake up to an alarm
still tired and are tired
throughout the day then there might be
other things going on as well
but we would like to see the people not
waking up to an alarm
tired um and then especially stimulants
like caffeine
are not universally bad for people
there's actually good research showing
that many times
in many cases they're healthy and
longevity supporting but using
stimulants
in place of sleep is bad for you and
this is what makes
adrenal burnout um and so
here's one thing i would say for
intelligence and psychological
well-being and health and everything is
re-prioritize sleep so that's one
two there are so many you know things i
could
say here but um study how to
how to learn i would say read a book on
systems theory
read some stuff on complexity
read some things on epistemology
read you know play with integral
philosophy and
see if i would say for every hour
invested in learning how to learn
then everything else that you're
learning is working through better
frameworks
and it has a over time exponential
positive
so um i'll call that number two
okay and also for integral philosophy do
you recommend
ken wilbur as the guy the go-to guy
that's the starting point
and this is not that someone's
necessarily going to be called to all of
it or agree with all of it ken did a
major synthesis work the quadrants came
from uh
jurgen habermas the hollows came from
arthur kessler
uh developmental psychology came from
you know
kohlberg and graves and so many people
so he he identified
really good meta theories or meaningful
at least insightful metatherapists and
brought a number of them together to be
able to look at
things like um human development
and so it is it's an insightful place to
look at a number of meaningful meta
theories
together um
and a brief history of everything is a
good
lay introduction to it and then one can
go further in different places and there
will be some stuff
that sounds kind of mystical
pseudosciencey and that's okay i would
again just
look at the underlying philosophic
structures um
and maybe number three now i will say
if someone is learning how to learn but
they're not actually learning content it
won't work you also
then have to be learning content like
whatever fields you're passionate about
study them more allocate more of your
life to
studying them and then as you're
studying them you actually get an
example of
applying those thinking models
and so it's the combination of those
that makes a huge difference
and then number three i would say uh in
you know just a straight kind of plug
for what we're doing
go check out the website yeah i mean
if qualia calls to uh then
by all means check it out and either way
there's a lot of information
on neurohacker.com and every day more is
getting up there about
how cognition works and the chemistry
that affects it and
uh over the next little while we're
planning on robusting that to be a very
meaningful
uh knowledge source for people so uh
awesome check it out cool so if you're
if you're able to
so i'm pulling up a bunch of new tabs on
my on my
desktop as you're throwing out of these
examples
of things to study if you were to
recommend one
book like your all-time favorite book
that just blew you away um that was
also consumable for uh
the average person what would that be
it's an impossible question uh
pick a book any book it's like asking
what my favorite nutrient is where you
can die of nutrient deficiency across
some meteor
um i don't think it's that serious
but the first book that popped to mind
is a
critical path by buck mr fuller oh great
okay
cool
all right i'm gonna get
my kindle so thank you very much daniel
schmuckenberger of the neurohacker
collective
this is our show uh and ben i admire
your courage going ahead with the
show even with a hurricane the very
first
landfall of a hurricane on costa rica
since 1851 so this is a historic show
and i
i think it's very fun that we've done it
i've really enjoyed this i learned a lot
i hope
people listening um uh we'll
get something tremendous out of it uh
thank you both good night
thank you everybody have a good one